Alright so today's דף Daf is י"ג, Yod Gimmel, we're a bit
behind, we are on, we pick up at the very bottom of
י"ב עמוד א'. Yod Bet Amud Aleph.
Currently the reason I got so stuck at the end of yesterday
was because actually this is a, this passage is much debated in
the commentators and it's quite difficult to explain. So I'm gonna give
you, it wasn't just me is what I'm saying, I'm gonna give
you the explanation of the תוספות הראש Tosafot HaRosh which is I
think the simplest. Okay, let's pick up from three lines from the
bottom on י"ב עמוד א'. Yod Bet Amud Aleph. רב יהודה בשם
רב דרבי אבהו רבי אבהו בשם רבי יוחנן Rav Yehuda beshem Rav
de-Rebbe Avu Rebbe Avu beshem Rebbe Yochanan קדשי בדק הבית שפדאן תמימים
יצאו לחולין. Kodshei Bedek HaBayit she-pede'an temimim yatze'u le-chullin. Okay, so remember
I told you there's two types of קדושה, Kedushah, בדק הבית Bedek
HaBayit is the one that's more about ownership, and therefore if you
sanctify an unblemished animal which you're not allowed to do to sanctify
for בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayit, but you went ahead and did it,
either explicitly or like our משנה Mishnah generically and it took effect,
so you sanctified an unblemished animal, so it looks like something that
could be a קרבן Korban but you sanctified it for בדק הבית
Bedek HaBayit and you redeemed it without a blemish, which you're entitled
to do because it's בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit and it's about ownership
and not about its purpose. So then the animal is totally יצא
לחולין. yatza le-chullin. It has no remnant of the קדושה. Kedushah. And
this is as opposed to a קרבן Korban which after it gets
a מום mum and you redeem it, you are not allowed to
shear it and to work it and to benefit from its milk
and so on. So here though you redeemed it and it has
nothing left of its קדושה Kedushah like normal בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit.
So the גמרא Gemara says מתניתין אמר כן, matnitin amar ken, our
משנה Mishnah says this and this is a משנה Mishnah in חולין,
Chullin, ולדן וחלבן מותר לאחר
פדיונם, vladan va-chalavan mutar le-achar pidyonam, their children and their milk is
permissible
after they've been redeemed. Now what is it talking about? The משנה
Mishnah over there in חולין Chullin is talking about a, actually it's
this is where it gets very complicated, but I'll really simplify, something
that actually was a
קרבן, Korban, קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbe'ach, but the scenario is is that
it had a blemish before you sanctified it. And what the משנה
Mishnah there does is it distinguishes between the two scenarios: you sanctify
an animal for a קרבן Korban and it gets a blemish, then
the original קדושה Kedushah was the full קדושה Kedushah of a קרבן.
Korban. Now it gets a blemish, you're allowed to redeem it, but
some of that קדושה, Kedushah, residual קדושה Kedushah will remain because originally
the full קדושה Kedushah was that of a קרבן. Korban. If it
started with a blemish, it was never really fit for the מזבח,
Mizbe'ach, and therefore when you sanctified it for the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, that
קדושה Kedushah is not so much a קדושת מזבח, Kedushas Mizbe'ach, like
if I sanctified my car for an עולה. Olah. Now obviously there's
a difference between sanctifying my car and my sheep with a blemish,
but there is something analogous between sanctifying an animal already with a
blemish and sanctifying something לבדק הבית, le-Bedek HaBayit, straight
for בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit. No, no. So, so what the משנה
Mishnah there says is, if this animal that you with a blemish
you sanctified for an עולה, Olah, after you redeem it there is
no residual קדושה, Kedushah, you can benefit from the milk and from
the children. So the גמרא Gemara here assumes, thank you, that what
is true by
a sanctity for the מזבח Mizbe'ach for a קרבן Korban if a
blemish preceded it is going to be the same as if you
sanctified it straight לבדק הבית. le-Bedek HaBayit. So you understand the analogy,
right? If I sanctified it straight for the temple treasury, it's not
about its use, and if I sanctified it for the מזבח Mizbe'ach
but it already had a blemish, it's also not really a sanctity
for a קרבן Korban and it says if in the second case
even when you try to sanctify as a קרבן Korban once you
when you redeem it you it's completely desanctified, the same would be
true when originally you only sanctified it לבדק הבית. le-Bedek HaBayit. Okay,
you have a question?
Does the person who sanctifies the animal for blemish realize it had
a blemish before sanctifying?
That's not clear and it doesn't really matter. I mean it matters
maybe if he transgressed because you're not allowed to sanctify an animal
with a blemish, but in terms of the nature of the קדושה,
Kedushah, well you could say, you know, in terms of yes, what
was in his mind and his דעת da'at and so on.
What I mean to say is if he did it without seeing
the blemish then perhaps the blemish came after he sanctified.
Oh, how do you know that it preceded it? Yeah, maybe witnesses
told him that it was there from beforehand. Maybe when he checked
it and its leg was torn off and you know something obvious.
Okay, but let's just get a little bit further in the גמרא,
Gemara, okay? So מתניתין אמר כן, matnitin amar ken, so ולדן וחלבן
מותר לאחר פדיונם, vladan va-chalavan mutar le-achar pidyonam, and that's by something
where a blemish preceded it and it was קדושת מזבח. Kedushas Mizbe'ach.
So presumably the same is true for קדושת בדק הבית Kedushas Bedek
HaBayit even without a blemish. Okay, so that's first a support. Now
let's see what it says on turn the page. רב חזקיה בשם
רב חסדא
הפטיר, Rav Chizkiyah beshem Rav Chisda hipatir, and רב חזקיה בשם רב
חסדא Rav Chizkiyah beshem Rav Chisda explains it, and this is where
it gets confusing because הפטיר hipatir is usually used to answer a
question but here it's sort of saying it rejects this. It says:
No, that's not necessarily a
support. That's when שפדאן תמימים והוממו. she-pede'an temimim ve-hummemu. Okay, now there's...
question here about the גרסא girsa *girsa*, but basically it means the
הגר"א *ha-Gra's*, which is the גרסא *girsa* which we will do because
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* you gotta do something to make sense out
of it. Okay, it would mean that explains it שחוממו ופדאן *she-hummu
u-p'da'an*, תפתר שחוממו ופדאן *tipater she-hummu u-p'da'an*, meaning the basic answer is
you cannot compare it. Yes, it's true that that was redeemed and
had no residual קדושה kedushah *kedushah*, but at least it had a
מום mum *mum*. And it's not necessarily true that the same is
true with something that is בדק הבית bedek habayit. *bedek ha-bayit* which
is unblemished. בדק הבית bedek habayit *bedek ha-bayit* unblemished, you know, nothing
problematic about it, it might still have some residual קדושה kedushah *kedushah*
and you cannot make that comparison. Now I still have to tell
you, I don't know, to me it seems like a very strong
comparison. If you fundamentally don't start with קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach. *kedushat
mizbe'ach*, you only start with בדק הבית bedek habayit. *bedek ha-bayit*, that's
a קדושה kedushah *kedushah* that could completely be removed. Whereas if you
start with קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach? *kedushat mizbe'ach*, you know, that's fundamentally
more problematic. But again, it seems that the concern might be more
about like practical concerns. If I see you using this animal after
you redeemed it and it's got a מום mum, *mum*, fine, I
understand it's got a מום mum *mum*, whatever. If I see you
using it after it's been redeemed and it's unblemished, and I knew
it was sanctified, that makes a lot more problems. So yes, it's
true, when the מום mum. *mum* preceded the sanctity, the קדושה kedushah,
*kedushah* for the altar might be very similar to קדושת בדק הבית
kedushat bedek habayit, *kedushat bedek ha-bayit* because it was never fit, but
it's still not so obvious that you can, there's no residual קדושה
kedushah *kedushah* in the case of an unblemished animal. I want to
build a little bit more and then I'll take the question, but
I just want to get a little bit further, okay. רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yosi בשם רב Rav חסדא *Rabbi Yosei b'shem Rav Chisda* מתניתין
אמרה כן *matnitin amrah ken*. He, now he says, the משנה mishnah.
*Mishnah* says this that he's still trying to prove again according to
the way the תוספות חדשים *Tosafot Chadashim* reads it, that you can
redeem it unblemished if it's בדק הבית bedek habayit *bedek ha-bayit* and
it's completely מותר mutar *mutar*, because that same משנה mishnah *Mishnah* says
that by the when it's sanctified for the altar and and it
got a מום mum. *mum* after it was sanctified, so then it
originally had full sanctity to the altar, it says ולדן וחלבן אסור
לאחר פדיונן *v'ladan v'chalavan asur l'achar pidyonan*. Actually this is also the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah* back in תמורה temurah, *Temurah*. It says this is
a difference between קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbe'ach, *kodshei mizbe'ach* and קדשי בדק
הבית bedek habayit, *kodshei bedek ha-bayit*. That קדשי מזבח mizbe'ach *kodshei mizbe'ach*
if they get a מום mum. *mum* afterwards, then it remains אסור
*asur*, okay. So he says, ah, but the implication is that קדשי
בדק הבית bedek habayit *kodshei bedek ha-bayit*, right, would actually become מותר
*mutar* afterwards. Now of course you're going to say, yeah, after it
got a מום mum? *mum*. So that so what he might be
doing is might be trying to reinforce the idea that you cannot
assume that if you redeem it unblemished it is okay because here
when is it okay by קדשי מזבח Mizbe'ach *kodshei mizbe'ach*? It is
what, what's the context of קדשי מזבח mizbeach, *kodshei mizbe'ach*? Again and
in a case when it is blemished. So let me just don't
cry, it's getting very confusing, okay. But you have basically, you have
a משנה mishnah *Mishnah* in חולין chulin. *Chullin*, I know it doesn't
even say where it's from, but anyway you have a משנה mishnah
*Mishnah* in חולין chulin? *Chullin* that basically said that if it's first
מום mum *mum* and then and then קדוש kadosh *kadosh*, okay, and
then you're מקדיש makdish *makdish* it קדשי מזבח mizbe'ach, *kodshei mizbe'ach*, the
מום mum *mum* came first. So since the מום mum? *mum* came
first, okay, this is somewhat comparable to
בדק הבית bedek habayit. *bedek ha-bayit* because it was never fit.
And in that case, so that you have to remember the סוגיא
*sugya* in חולין Chullin.
*Chullin*, but it's somewhat comparable.
And in that case the הלכה halacha *halachah* is that after that
ולדן וחלבן מותר *v'ladan
v'chalavan mutar*, which we say means that it is יצא לחולין *yatza
l'chulin*. Even that could be debated, just because חלבן מותר *chalavan mutar*
doesn't mean it's completely יצא לחולין *yatza l'chulin*. Okay, so that's what
we say, so that's the proof that when it's בדק הבית Bedek
HaBayis *bedek ha-bayit* it's completely יצא לחולין *yatza l'chulin*. Okay, that was
the proof. The answer is no, because even if it's somewhat comparable,
at least it has a מום mum? *mum*. Okay, and that מום
mum, *mum* ultimately might be what allows it to be completely יצא
לחולין *yatza l'chulin* even though the קדושות *kedushot* are comparable, which is
תמים *tamim*. Okay, so then we go over here to a משנה
mishna? *Mishnah* in תמורה temurah, *Temurah*, which said, here's the difference between
בדק הבית Bedek Habayit *bedek ha-bayit* and מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. That by
קדשי מזבח mizbe'ach. *kodshei mizbe'ach* if it gets a קדוש kadosh, *kadosh*
and then מום mum *mum*, okay, then ולדן וחלבן אסור *v'ladan v'chalavan
asur*, which basically means implicitly that by בדק הבית Bedek Habayit. *bedek
ha-bayit*, okay, if the ולדן וחלבן מותר *v'ladan v'chalavan mutar*, right, which
means that it is יצא לחולין *yatza l'chulin*. But again, in a
comparable case, what's a comparable case? That there was some מום mum?
*mum*. So the argument in both cases is yes, here by implicit
contrast it's יצא לחולין *yatza l'chulin*, here by implicit parallel it's יצא
לחולין *yatza l'chulin*, but in all of the cases we're talking about
a מום mum? *mum*. So you don't have a basis to say
that if there's no מום mum *mum* it actually would be completely
יצא לחולין *yatza l'chulin*. Okay, but again, the funny thing is that
a מום mum *mum* really shouldn't matter when it's בדק הבית Bedek
Habayit *bedek ha-bayit*, so even though it's a good point that in
all these cases there's a מום mum, *mum* and you can't prove
a case without a מום mum. *mum*, nevertheless. So basically what you're
saying is that even though it is a מום, mum and there's
no way you can touch this thing once they did, so basically
what you're saying is המבטא Hamivta or something like that? Yeah, I
do not want to get into that, okay? That's a discussion for
that משנה. mishna. Alright, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. So now we say, so רבי חזקיה בשם
רבי יוסי. Rebbi Chizkiyah beshem Rebbi Yosi. Now רבי חזקיה Rebbi Chizkiyah
in the name of רבי Rebbe יוסי said קדשי בדק הבית שפדאן
תמימים יצאו לחולין. kodshei bedek habayit shepdan tmimim yatzu l'chulin. He says
I'm sorry, I must insist on this position that they completely become
fully חולין. How do I know they completely become fully חולין? אי
תימא לא יצאו לחולין ei teima lo yatzu l'chulin because if they
wouldn't, היך קדשי מזבח חלין על קדשי בדק הבית? heich kodshei mizbe'ach
chalin al kodshei bedek habayit?
How could you ever turn it into a קרבן? korban? How do
you know you turn it into a קרבן? korban? Because what does
our משנה Mishna say? You remember our משנה Mishna according to רבי
יהושע?
Rebbi Yehoshua? You sanctified everything generically. He says the unblemished things are
not. According to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, he says the unblemished things
are בדק הבית. Bedek Habayit? But what do I do? It's a
male sheep and unblemished and whatever. So I sell it to you,
you need to bring an עולה, olah, right? The money goes to
בדק הבית Bedek Habayit and you go ahead and bring an עולה.
olah. How do you bring an עולה? olah? If it was not,
if it wasn't fully יצאו לחולין, yatzu l'chulin, if it still had
some קדושה kedushah on it, you can't give it a different קדושה
kedushah now. You can only sanctify something for a קרבן korban that's
completely desanctified. So he said it's clear in our משנה Mishna that
when you redeem an unblemished animal לבדק הבית, l'bedek habayit, the animal
can be used as a קרבן, korban, which means it was totally
יצאו לחולין, yatzu l'chulin, which is a pretty good argument. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. קדשי מזבח חלה עליהם. kodshei mizbe'ach
chalah aleihem. Okay. אי תימא לא יצאו לחולין היך קדשי מזבח חלה
על קדשי בדק הבית. ei teima lo yatzu l'chulin heich kodshei mizbe'ach
chalah al kodshei bedek habayit. So בעלי מומין, ba'alei mumin, קדשי מזבח
חלה עליהם, kodshei mizbe'ach chalah aleihem, לדא מילתא. l'da milta. Now let's
say you have something that is קדשי מזבח, mizbeiah. this gets back
to the משנה Mishnah, in חולין. It starts with a blemish and
you sanctify it for as a קרבן. korban. So I said it's
not really fit for a קרבן. korban. It's somewhat parallel to as
like you sanctified it לבדק הבית, l'bedek habayit, right? Because it starts
by being unfit. It's like I sanctified my car for an עולה.
olah. But it's not completely. At the end of the day it
still is, it's not completely בדק הבית. Bedek Habayit. At the end
of the day you still try to give it a קדושה kedushah
of a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says לדא מילתא, l'da
milta, לאיזה דבר, l'eizeh davar, for what purpose when you sanctify an
animal with a blemish for a קרבן, korban, is it, does it
have some element of a קדושת קרבן? kedushat korban? Not just the
קדושת בדק הבית, kedushat bedek habayit, even though it started unfit. Okay,
so לדא מילתא, l'da milta, for what purpose? So it said לגז
ולעבודה, l'giza ul'avodah, that still before you, before you, you cannot shear
it and work it, okay, and it still is prohibited, you know,
to be for those purposes. So one minute, just one second. Right.
Because if I sanctified this cow, this was discussed the other day.
Let's say I need a cow to plow a field. I can
sanctify it לבדק הבית l'bedek habayit and then use it to plow
a field. Let's say I want to sanctify my flock for בדק
הבית bedek habayit. so that they can use the wool to make
the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. I can do that. It's just their
property. So it is מותר in גיזה ועבודה. giza va'avodah. But if
it is קדוש kadosh, as a קרבן, korban, then its whole קדושה,
kedushah its whole sort of purpose and identity is to be brought
as a קרבן korban and it can't be used for anything else.
So this animal with a מום mum, that I sanctified, if I
really had sanctified it for בדק הבית, bedek habayis you could work
it, you could shear it, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash could, not
me, okay? But if I sanctified it, but because it's קדושת קרבן,
kedushat korban, although it's a מום, mum. then you cannot do גיזה
ועבודה. giza va'avodah. So although here we said when it starts with
a מום mum? and then קדש למזבח, kadosh l'mizbe'ach, it's almost like
sanctifying my car, almost, but not quite. It's still a sheep and
I still try to do קדושת מזבח. kedushat mizbe'ach And the difference
between this and בדק הבית bedek habayis, is here, if it was
straight לבדק הבית, l'bedek habayit, I could shear it, I could work
it, the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not me. And here they cannot
because it still has aspects of קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. Okay. Again,
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash had fields and workers? Presume, I mean,
or if they did, but presumably they did. One minute, it's theoretical.
Right. I don't know exactly, but if they wanted to, they could
shear it and sell it and so on. So the כהונה kehunah
didn't own fields, but they- Yeah, but the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
could. A כהן kohen didn't, but the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was like the Vatican, it's got its own
bank account, its own treasury, it's got whatever, להבדיל. l'havdil. What? How
would the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash acquire fields? You sanctify the parcel,
and by- you sanctify your field to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Somebody does. So it would have to come from donations. Yeah, or
they took leftover money that they had from various things and they
invested it in fields. They bought what? That they could do business
transactions with private individuals. Yeah. Okay. So just now what? You sanctified
your animal with a מום. mum. We just a minute ago we
said it was parallel to קדושת בדק הבית, kedushat bedek habayis but
not exactly בדק הבית. Bedek ha-Bayis? You still tried to sanctify it
for a קרבן korban even though it had a מום. mum. So
for what purpose does it still have an aspect of קדושת מזבח?
kedushat mizbe'ach That you can't use it for. Here you redeem it
and what was חלב ודם chalav v'dam mutar for you, not the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Here you redeem בדק הבית and you can
use חלב ודם. chalav v'dam. But let's say you didn't redeem it.
So when this was still קדוש, kadosh. the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
could go into business with this. When this was קדוש, kadosh, they
could not because it's קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. But yeah, thank you
for pointing that out. Yes. Doesn't it have to be inspected before?
Yeah, but this was private individuals that sanctified. Okay. Yeah. No. Okay,
so it says, let's take a look. Okay, לגיזה ולעבודה. l'gizah u'l'avodah.
Now, הפריש נקבה—now hifrish nekevah that's קדושת בדק הבית—a kedushat bedek habayit.
מום. mum. Here now we're going to ask what about things that
are parallel to a מום? mum Again, if it was my car
and I did it לקדושת מזבח, l'kedushat mizbe'ach, maybe it
just would be like
a toast. Okay, but what about something that's not necessarily a מום
mum but not necessarily my car? Like what? הפריש נקבה לעולתו. hifrish
nekevah l'olaso. I set aside a female sheep for and I sanctified
it for an עולה, olah, right? Is that like a מום mum
or not like a מום? Mum? Or is it worse than a
מום? Mum? What's the story? Okay, ולפסחו ולאשמו, u'l'pischo u'l'ashamo, or for
my פסח Pesach or for my אשם, asham, all things that you
need male sheep for. So, עושה תמורה. oseh temurah. So the first
opinion is that it has קדושת מזבח Kidushat Mizbe'ach enough that you
can do a תמורה, temurah right? You know תמורה, temurah, it's always
funny when you talk about a תמורה temurah, because it's prohibited, you
transgress when you do it, but it's always a discussion, well, is
it effective? I mean, under what circumstance the תורה Torah says even
though you transgress, you the other things, you don't remove the קדושה
kedushah of the first, but you have, you create קדושה kedushah, on
the second animal. You tried to say this in exchange for that,
you transgress a biblical prohibition, the first one did not change its
status, but the second one became קדוש. kadosh Okay, and that is
so that is all by קרבנות korbanos and it's not a process
of redeeming, it's an attempt
to exchange when the animal is unblemished or whatever you
redeem קרבנות korbanos even if it has a blemish on money,
you don't exchange
it for another animal.
So when you try to do that and you did a תמורה,
temurah?
the second one becomes קדוש, kadosh.
the first one does not get removed. So let's say I sanctified
this female sheep as a פסח, Pesach, okay, and then I said
זו תמורת זו zo temuras zo
on a male sheep, okay? So the first one the קדושה kedusha?
doesn't get removed.
Does the second sheep have קדושת עולה kedushat olah or not, right?
To what degree is the first
one have enough קדושת קרבן kedushat korban that when I
try to do this תמורה, temurah? when it's able to take effect
on the second one,
the second one actually does become a תמורה? temurah, Okay, so it's
similar to this לגיזה ולעבודה l'gizah u'l'avodah question. We've said that with
a מום,
it still has enough קדושת קרבן kedushat korban even when it starts
with a מום that it's אסור בגיזה ועבודה. asur b'gizah v'avodah. How
about something that's not a מום? It's a female when you need
a male, and is that enough in the פרשה parsha or not?
So and the test case is will it be עושה תמורה? oseh
temurah? Will it be able to, you know, again you would transgress
but would it make a תמורה? temurah, So let's take a look.
הפריש נקבה לעולתו לפסחו ולאשמו hifrish nekevah l'olaso l'pischo u'l'ashamo עושה תמורה.
oseh temurah. So the first position is yes, it does make a
תמורה, temurah. it does have enough קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. רבי שמעון
אומר לעולתו עושה תמורה. Rabbi Shimon omer l'olaso oseh temurah. For an
עולה olah it will, you know, this sheep if you try to
make it an עולה, olah, then it will be able to make
a תמורה, tmura, so there was קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. לפסחו ולאשמו
אין עושה תמורה, l'pischo u'l'ashamo ein oseh temurah, but
not for your פסח Pesach and your אשם. asham. Why?
Obviously the question. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון לעולתו
לפסחו ולאשמו אין עושה תמורה.
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi
Shimon
l'olaso l'pischo u'l'ashamo ein oseh temurah. Not for any. So one opinion
for all of them, one opinion for none of them, and one
that distinguishes between an עולה olah on one side and פסח Pesach
and an אשם asham on the other. And the last two are
attributed to the same תנא. Tanna. Well, yes, one is רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and one is a tradition in the name of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן טעמא דרבי
שמעון. Amar Rabbi Yochanan ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon. The reason of the first
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that it works that distinguishes between
עולה olah is good and פסח Pesach and אשם asham not, or
עולה olah it has some of that קדושה kedusha, and not פסח
Pesach and אשם, asham, שכן מצינו נקבה בעוף כשרה לבוא עולה, sheken
matzinu nekevah b'of kesherah lavo olah, because if you bring a bird
קרבן korban for an עולה, olah, it can be a female. Okay,
so therefore when I give it sanctity of an עולה, olah, this
animal that's this female sheep, what's the thing that's that makes it
inappropriate? That it's a female. But the concept of female by עולה
olah is not foreign. And since the concept of female by עולה
olah is not totally foreign, it actually does get the קדוש kadosh
enough קדושה kedusha. as opposed to by פסח Pesach and אשם asham
that's completely foreign, so it's not enough קדושה kedusha of מזבח that
it can make a תמורה. tmura, That's his reason. Okay, ואמר רבי
יוחנן טעמא דרבי שמעון בן יהודה. v'amar Rabbi Yochanan ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda. Now what's רבי שמעון בן יהודה's Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
reason that says it doesn't get for anything the it's not עושה
תמורה, oseh temurah, okay, that for none of them? So he says
טעמא דרבי שמעון בן יהודה ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda אם מין
במינו הוא חלוק עליו. im min b'mino hu chaluk alav. If something
that's basically the same fundamental type of thing is different enough that
it would not have קדושה, kedusha. so כל שכן מין שאינו. kol
sheken min she-eino. Or קדושת מזבח Kidushat Mizbe'ach at least not. Certainly
מין שאינו, min she-eino, something that's of a foreign thing, that's a
female when you needed a male. So איזהו מין במינו שהוא חולק
עליו? eizehu min b'mino she-hu cholek alav? What's the case where מין
במינו min b'mino is completely different? כהדא דתניא, kehada d'tanya, like we
taught, אשם בן שנה ואשם בן שתיים. asham ben shanah v'asham ben
shtayim. You needed a one-year-old, some אשם asham it have to be
one-year-old, some have to be two years old. You needed a one-year-old
and you sanctified a two-year-old. So think about it. It's an unblemished
animal, it's the right animal, and it's an אשם asham which for
אשם asham some אשמים ashamim one-year-olds work and some two-year-olds work. So
it's like totally in the פרשה, parsha, right? Totally appropriate for an
אשם asham just not for this אשם, asham, but otherwise right animal,
right gender, right everything. Okay, or בן שתיים והביא בן שלוש. ben
shtayim v'hevi ben shalosh. You needed a two-year-old and you brought a
three-year-old. לא יצא. lo yatza. Now, you're not יוצא yotzei your קרבן,
korban, fine. But what does that tell you about the קדושה? kedusha
So most מפרשים meforshim read the next line, which is רבי שמעון
אומר כל עצמן אינם קדושים. Rabbi Shimon omer kol atzman einam kedoshim.
Not only were you not יוצא, yotzei, the animal doesn't even become
קדוש. kadosh So since this is a tradition in the name of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he says look, if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
himself says that even a difference between a one-year-old and a two-year-old,
even when an אשם asham allows in some cases for a two-year-old,
if that means it doesn't get any קדושה, kedusha, how much more
so a female for a male when a female is completely unrelated?
No, so the question is what he says, how would it be
different than
the case through here of מום?
He might say that the issue of a wrong age or a
wrong gender is more fundamentally different. It's like being מקדיש makdish your
car. It may be more fundamentally different than even a מום and
it gets no קדושה. kedusha Different than מום because like in an
עולה, olah, if it's just like, let's say, a problem with the
eye, then that'll be okay then you should be fine with that,
but it's missing a leg, it's never even good for an עולה.
olah. I know, but but again, if it's fundamentally they might take
a position. First you decide if it's in the right category. Something
that's not in the right category, not the right age, not the
right gender, whatever, it might as well be my automobile. If it's
in the category and then and it has a מום, that already
puts it more in the פרשה. parsha. That seems to be the
way of thinking, even if it's a serious מום. That seems to
be the assumption here. Okay, we'll see more of this, don't worry,
we're not done with this discussion. Okay, so you have this range
of positions. Either that it gets קדושה kedusha, and it's sort of
like the מום case, although here we're talking about תמורה, tmura not
גיזת ועבודה, gizat v'avoda, or none of it gets קדושה. kedusha It's
more fundamentally in a different category, even a difference of years would
put it in a different category, or a difference between עולה olah
and the other things. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said Rav
Yochanan, רבי שמעון ורבי יהושע שניהם אמרו דבר אחד. Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi
Yehoshua shneihem amru davar echad. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua say essentially the same thing. Okay, what does that mean?
כמדא דרבי יהושע אמר נקבה לעולה לא קידשה אלא הקדש דמים. k'mada
d'Rabbi Yehoshua amar nekeiva l'olah lo kidsha ela hekdesh damim. So רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, right, so remember the case, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says I sanctify this is where we started, all my property
generically. So the female unblemished animals get קדושת עולה, kedushat olah, right?
Remember he said that. What do I have to do? I have
to basically go ahead and transfer the money and then use the
proceeds to buy an עולה olah and have somebody bring that female
as a שלמים. shlamim. Remember that from רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in
the משנה? Mishnah. Okay. So he said look at it, here you
go, it's a case, it's a female, right? It's a female and
it was a generic קדושה kedusha and we still allow the קדושת
עולה kedushat olah to take effect. So that basically means that the
קדושה, kedusha if you're מקדיש makdish a female for an עולה, olah,
it's meaningful enough that that קדושה kedusha takes effect, right? We don't
say oh it's completely out of the פרשה parsha and therefore should
just be קדושת בדק הבית. Kidushat Bedek Habayit. Alright, he allows for
a קדושת עולה kedushat olah to take effect on the female animal
and then you sell the proceeds and you use it. So that's
what he says. כן רבי שמעון אומר נקבה לעולה לא קידשה אלא
הקדש דמים. ken Rabbi Shimon omer nekeiva l'olah lo kidsha ela hekdesh
damim. I'm sorry, did I misread that? לא קידשה אלא הקדש דמים.
lo kidsha ela hekdesh damim. Hold on, did I misread that? רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that you're מוכר mocher it לצורך l'tzorech נקבה
ימכרו לצורך זבחי שלמים ויביא בדמיהן עולות. nekeiva yimachru l'tzorech zivchei shlamim
v'yavi bidmeihen olot. So one second, what's the הקדש דמים, hekdesh damim,
I'm sorry just one second. Oh no, no, no, here's the mistake
I made, I'm sorry. The point being that when you sell this
animal is the נקבה nekeiva that becomes קדוש Kadosh and you're going
to use the proceeds for an עולה, olah, you redeem it without
a מום, right? You redeem that animal even though it is unblemished,
right? Get the scenario? You sanctify all your property, the female sheep
according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua become קדוש for an עולה, olah,
you redeem it, you use the money for an עולה, olah, this
gets used for זבחי שלמים. zivchei shlamim. But you redeem it without
a מום. How are you allowed to redeem it without a מום?
It must be the fact that it is a נקבה nekeiva is
a big enough problem that it essentially puts it out of the
פרשה parsha and allows you to redeem it without a מום. So
let's take a look at that, okay? It rolls it out. כמדא
דרבי יהושע אמר נקבה לעולה לא קידשה אלא הקדש דמים, k'mada d'Rabbi
Yehoshua amar nekeiva l'olah lo kidsha ela hekdesh damim, which again means
that you can, we'll see in a minute, means you can redeem
it without a מום. Okay. כן רבי שמעון אומר, ken Rabbi Shimon
omer, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, נקבה לעולה לא קידשה אלא
הקדש דמים, nekeiva l'olah lo kidsha ela hekdesh damim, and says that
in all animals even a נקבה nekeiva for an עולה olah that
it does not make a תמורה, Tmurah it's only הקדש דמים. hekdesh
damim. אם תימר קידשה קדושת הגוף, im teimar kidsha kedushat haguf, if
it's an intrinsic קדושה, kedusha, ירעו, yiru, then it should have to
graze before you are allowed to redeem it in the משנה. mishnah?
Now what's the difference between תמורה tmura. and הקדש דמים? hekdesh damim?
Okay, so thank you. Actually, so here, look, this is, it is
complicated. I need to explain another concept, which is the following, because
normally there's an assumption that I've been basically saying, what's the fundamental
difference between קדושת מזבח Kidushat Mizbe'ach and קדושת בדק הבית. Kidushat Bedek
Habayit. Is that מזבח is about its identity and its purpose and
its use as a קרבן, korban, and בדק הבית is about ownership.
Okay, that is a simplification. It's not exactly precise because he says
think about this case where you sanctified an עולה olah for a
female sheep for your עולה. olah. Okay, so you can redeem it
without a blemish. Okay, so that's הקדש דמים Hekdesh Damim what it
says. We would call that בדק הבית. But it's not really בדק
הבית because what does Rabbi Yehoshua in the משנה mishnah say you
do after you redeem the עולה olah sheep? What do you do
with the money? You use it to buy what? An עולה. olah.
No, an עולה. olah. The sheep goes on no, an עולה. olah.
So it's so make up your mind. How do you both, here's
the point, and this is the very important part coming up. How
is it both able to be redeemed without a blemish, but the
money has the קדושה kedusha of an עולה olah and you use
it to buy an עולה olah and it doesn't go to בדק
הבית? So it's very, this is a very subtle point that a
lot of people get confused about. There's a difference between קדושת דמים
Kidushat Damim and קדושת הגוף Kidushat HaGuf and קדושת מזבח Kidushat Mizbe'ach.
and קדושת בדק הבית. קדושת דמים Kidushat Damim and קדושת הגוף Kidushat
HaGuf is really the more precise terms of what I was talking
about before, which is קדושת דמים Kidushat Damim is it's not this
thing is not going to be used itself. Only it's going to
be sold and something else is going to be used with the
proceeds. That's קדושת דמים. Kidushat Damim. קדושת הגוף Kidushat HaGuf is this
thing is going to be used itself. Now, normally that would normally
be בדק הבית versus קרבן, korban, but I'll give you exceptions to
the rule. Okay, something that has קדושת הגוף Kidushat HaGuf that's בדק
הבית. How can it be? I sanctified a beam or a stone
to be put into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or you know
or that's קדושת הגוף Kidushat HaGuf but it's לבדק הבית. LiBedek Habayit.
It's for, it's not for a קרבן. korban. קדושת דמים למזבח Kidushat
Damim LiMizbe'ach is our case. The sheep is not going to be
used itself. So it only has, and it never said, it never
was able to be used itself. It's not like it was and
it got a מום. Then it would still have a קדושת הגוף
Kidushat HaGuf that somehow not usable. This thing was never able to
be, so it only initially got a קדושת דמים. Kidushat Damim. It
only, which means a sanctity to be transferred and used in something
else, not to be used intrinsically. That's like the קדושת דמים למזבח.
Kidushat Damim LiMizbe'ach. Okay, so it's a קדושה kedusha, of value, what
are you going to do with, you're not going to use it,
you're going to use its proceeds, but you're going to use it
למזבח LiMizbe'ach for a קרבן. korban. So that allowed for this very
interesting hybrid. I can redeem it without a blemish, right? I can
redeem it without a blemish because it's about its proceeds, it's not
about the thing itself. But the purpose of its value and its
קדושה kedusha, is למזבח, LiMizbe'ach, so I use that money to buy
an עולה. olah. Okay, so that was a lot, but that is
the basic concept of in the משנה mishnah, why you are allowed
to sell it and bring an עולה, olah, because it's קדושה למזבח,
Kedusha LiMizbe'ach, but why you're allowed to redeem it and sell it
without a מום because it's קדושת דמים. Kidushat Damim. It was never
about it itself; it was always about its proceeds. So that explains
Rabbi Yehoshua in the משנה mishna, and that also explains the position
here in the name of Rabbi Shimon that it's never עושה תמורה.
oseh tmura. If it initially its קדושה kedusha was only קדושת דמים,
Kidushat Damim, it is never עושה תמורה, oseh tmura, and that's why
it says it has a קדושת דמים. Kidushat Damim. Okay, so that
was pretty complicated. I hope you got some of that. All right,
so let's take a look. So okay, fine. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi,
now another statement. Says Rabbi, אני רואה, Ani ro'eh, now I gotta
tell you, all the מפרשים meforshim say they have to switch the
גירסא girsa to אין אני רואה. Ein ani ro'eh. Okay, we'll just
go with it. אין אני רואה דברי רבי שמעון בפסח שהמותיר פסח
בא שלמים. Ein ani ro'eh divrei Rabbi Shimon bePesach, she'mosar Pesach ba
shelamim. To Rabbi Shimon that says if you make a פסח, Pesach,
you try to sanctify a female for a פסח, Pesach, that it
does not have, that it does not have קדושת קרבן, Kidushat Korban,
I mean it does not have קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbeach, whatever, it
doesn't עושה תמורה. oseh tmura. He says I don't agree with him,
because actually a פסח Pesach is in the פרשה parsha of, a
female is in the פרשה parsha of פסח. Pesach. How is a
female in the פרשה parsha of a פסח? Pesach? Because if you
didn't bring it as a פסח Pesach and it's now after פסח,
Pesach, you can bring it as a שלמים. shelamim. So he says
when you sanctify a female for a פסח, Pesach, that's pretty much
in the פרשה, parsha, you know? So therefore it should be עושה
תמורה, oseh tmura, it should have קדושת מזבח. kedushat mizbeach. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says ולימא אין אני רואה דברי רבי שמעון
באשם שהמותיר אשם בא עולה. v'leima Ein ani ro'eh divrei Rabbi Shimon
beAsham, she'mosar Asham ba olah. One minute, if that's true, so why
doesn't he also say I don't agree with Rabbi Shimon by an
אשם Asham who says that it doesn't get קדושה, kedusha, because if
you leave, because what do you do by if you have leftover
money for an אשם? Asham? If you sanctified your money for an
אשם Asham and you didn't use all of it, what does the
leftover money go to? So the הלכה halacha is it goes to
an עולה. olah. Now an עולה... olah... Now, an עולה olah also
has to be a male, but Rabbi Shimon said actually when you
sanctify an עולה olah that's a female, an עולה olah that's a
female's in the פרשה parsha because you have a bird, because you
have birds that are females. Okay, so sort of like two steps.
Okay, רבי says, if you sanctify a פסח pesach that's a נקבה,
nekevah, that should be in the פרשה parsha because a פסח pesach
comes as שלמים. shlamim. Okay, so same thing. If you sanctify a
female for an אשם, asham, that should be in the פרשה parsha
because an אשם asham becomes used as an עולה, olah, and an
עולה olah as a bird can come as a נקבה. nekevah. So
okay, so it's both two steps. But the גמרא Gemara says why
not? So rather than pointing out the two steps, the גמרא Gemara
has a better answer. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this: Wait,
an עולה olah at a higher level of קדושה kedusha, than an
אשם? asham? I wouldn't talk about higher, I mean in the sense
that it's burnt completely, yes, but they're both קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim.
Okay, אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, if he sanctified a פסח
pesach as a שלמים, shlamim, גופו קרב שלמים. gufo karev shlamim. No,
there's a difference. Rabbi Shimon says the פסח pesach is really, a
female really is in the פרשה parsha because the animal itself will
be brought as a שלמים shlamim after פסח. pesach. If he sanctified
an אשם asham as an עולה, olah, you sanctified an אשם asham
and now you can't use it as an אשם, asham, let's say
the owner died or something else and you bring it as an
עולה, olah, אין גופו קרב עולה. ein gufo karev olah. You don't
bring the אשם asham itself as an עולה, olah, you redeem its
value and you transfer it to an עולה. olah. So there's a
huge difference. A פסח, pesach, a female's much more in the פרשה
parsha of פסח pesach because the animal itself can be brought as
a שלמים shlamim under the right circumstances. Whereas by an אשם asham
and an עולה, olah, the animal itself will never be brought as
an עולה. olah. Okay, מהו כדון? mahu kedon? So what's going on
here, meaning what's the debate about? הדין אמר הקדיש דמים הקדיש והין
אמר הקדיש גופו הקדיש. Hadayn amar hektish damim hektish v'hayn amar hektish
gufo hektish. One says you basically sanctified it קדושת דמים kedushat damim
and the other's a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Meaning what is the
debate, whatever position you take, you know, when this animal's a female,
does it, is it עושה תמורה oseh tmurah or not עושה תמורה?
oseh tmurah? At the end of the day it's a question whether
as a female does it get קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf or does
it get קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, okay? And this is again this
issue about, you know, about how is this, how much is the
fact that it's the wrong gender like the idea of a מום
or makes it even more out of the פרשה. parsha. Okay, and
that's the question. If it's full, more fully out of the פרשה,
parsha, if I try to sanctify my car for an עולה. olah.
Now what if I did that? This actually is a great example
of קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim lamizbeach. I sanctified my car for
an עולה. olah. Okay, what would you do with it? So you
know what you would do with it? Tell me what you would
do with it. Sell it and buy an עולה. olah. So that's
קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim lamizbeach. Okay, so when I sanctify my
female sheep for an עולה, olah, is it קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf
gone awry and therefore it's עושה תמורה? oseh tmurah? Or is it
קדושת דמים למזבח kedushat damim lamizbeach but it's still קדושת דמים kedushat
damim and therefore it's not עושה תמורה? oseh tmurah? Okay, so that
is the issues going around here of how to deal with a
case of the wrong gender, yes. And the thing that they never
consider is if I point to a female animal and say זה
עולה, zeh olah, that I haven't come, I haven't said anything. Oh,
about a toe. Yeah, okay, so we're not going to worry about
that. We try to make, we work with the assumption אין אדם
מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi devarav levatalah, meaning we want to
make your statements halachically meaningful and we sort of bracket, you know,
your intention. Yes, is this an accurate way of trying to imagine
this? Because you're talking about something that contains קדושה, kedusha. residue of
קדושה, kedusha, like is it the difference between being מקדיש Makdish something
under certain conditions in which you've put like a post-it on it
that can then be somehow removed and put on something else, right,
as opposed to injecting a piece of fabric with dye in which
then trying to take it out there's some... Well, the point is
that sometimes you do have some residue, so that's why I use
that as a metaphor. But you're right, I mean all of this
is, you know, you could say it's a metaphor, you could also
say it's a metaphysics, right, that they're really trying to imagine. Yeah,
so I am using it that way because sometimes you do have
what's essentially residual. Okay, yes. But it's easier to say, like, you
know, in the case of the car for the עולה, olah, everyone's
like, of course you can't bring a car on the מזבח, it's
just going to בדק הבית. No, what do you mean? I want
this to be used towards the funds for an עולה, olah, and
so we'll interpret it that way. That's the way to give meaningful
interpretation, right, but we can always, again, you can always say I
want it to be meaningful, I want it to be used in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yeah, we don't, at the end of
the day, we go by what you said, not by what maybe
you were thinking. And if what you said can be translated in
a meaningful way, then that's what we're going to go by. Okay.
He never had a car in the גמרא. Gemara, רבי זירא בשם
רבי שמעון לקיש. Rabbi Zeira b'shem Rabbi Shimon Lakish. Okay, we're up,
we gotta get a little bit, alright. רבי זירא בשם רבי שמעון
לקיש, Rabbi Zeira b'shem Rabbi Shimon Lakish, טעמיה דרבי יהושע, ta'ama d'Rabbi
Yehoshua, the reasoning of Rabbi Yehoshua is that now we're finally back
to the משנה, but we haven't abandoned this other discussion completely. So
what's the reason that Rabbi Yehoshua says when you sanctify things generically,
the things that are unblemished animals get קדושת מזבח, kedushas mizbeiah right?
Remember that was Rabbi Yehoshua in the משנה. So he said you
sanctified all your property but the animals get קדושת מזבח. kedushas mizbeiah.
So he says, דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו ואל כל בני ישראל
ואמרת אליהם איש איש מבית ישראל אשר יקריב לה' לעולה. dabeir el
Aharon v'el banav v'el kol bnei yisrael v'amarta aleihem ish ish mibeit
yisrael asher yakriv l'Hashem l'olah. So as opposed to when we explained
Rabbi Eliezer that said everything is לבדק הבית l'bedek habayit and he
quoted a פסוק. pasuk. Here רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is quoting a
פסוק pasuk about sanctifying קרבנות, korbanot, and therefore this is the general
rule. The general rule is, if it's in the פרשה parsha of
קרבנות, korbanot, the generic קדושה kedusha is קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. הכל
קרב לעולה. hakol kareiv l'olah. Everything will be sanctified for an עולה,
olah, right? Because also remember, he doesn't just say it gets קדושת
קרבן. kedushat korban. If it's a female, it doesn't become קדוש לשלמים.
kadosh l'shlamim. That would have been easy. No, it gets קדוש לעולה
kadosh l'olah and you have to sell it and transfer. Okay, now
one of those logics given is, not said here in the גמרא,
Gemara that an עולה olah is comparable to בדק הבית in the
sense that it's fully to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. But here
he's basing it on a פסוק. pasuk. Any generic קדושה, kedusha, if
it's being applied to unblemished animals, becomes קדושת עולה. kedushat olah. הכל
קרב לעולה. hakol kareiv l'olah. לרצונכם l'ratzonchem now the פסוק pasuk continues
תמים זכר, tamim zachar, okay, for your desire should be unblemished male.
So how does now he include the females, because he included unblemished
females, right, for to get this in the משנה? מנין אפילו נקבות?
minayin afilu nekeivos? תלמוד לומר בבקר, talmud lomar babakar, because it just
says cattle. Cattle's generic. לרבות את הנקבות, l'rabos es hanekeivos, even though
just a minute ago it said male. So the גמרא Gemara says
נו, nu, okay, בבקר. babakar. So of course the question is, now
let's include then blemished animals, right? So רבי יצחק בר רבי אלעזר
Rebbe Yitzchak be Rebbe Eliezer שאל, shal, כתיב זכר ksiv zachar ואמרת
בבקר v'amart babakar לרבות את הנקבות. l'rabos es hanekeivos. So it's very
nice what you just did. The פסוק pasuk says male, but you
said oh, but the other word says בקר, bakar, so I'll say
even a female. הכי נמי, hachi nami, if you're gonna do that,
דנימא הכי, d'neima hachi, say the same thing, כתיב תמים, ksiv tamim,
it says unblemished, ואמרת בבקר לרבות בעלי מומין. v'amart babakar l'rabos ba'alei
mumin. So say okay, בבקר babakar is to include even בעלי מומין.
ba'alei mumin. So why does he say when you sanctify your whole
property this קדושת עולה kedushat olah applies to the unblemished males and
females, let it apply even to the blemished ones? So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, מה ביניהון, mah beineihon, what difference does it make
that you allow it to apply to the females but you don't
apply it to the blemished ones? So רב Rav, אמר, amar, שבטא
דקדקא ביניהון, shivta d'kadka beineihon, the rod that you use in weaving,
basically there was a long rod that you would use to bang
out, you know, when you made a weave in the loom and
to smooth everything out. So that's what's between them. What does that
mean? It's like saying it's like a yardstick between them. There's a
mile of a difference between them. You can figure it out. And
the simple difference is, so what the מפרשים Mefarshim try to say
is, רב, there's a big difference between something that fundamentally can be
brought as a קרבן korban like an unblemished female sheep, not as
an עולה olah but as a קרבן, korban, fundamentally it could be
brought, as opposed to something that has a מום that fundamentally cannot.
But I do want to point out a little bit of the
irony, because a minute ago we were talking about being the wrong
gender being more out of the פרשה, parsha, and here we're talking
about it being, you know, in the פרשה parsha to get this
קדושה, Kedushah, this generic קדושה. Kedushah Okay, but that is the interesting
point. So in the משנה you have this generic קדושה, Kedushah it
takes effect on all the unblemished ones, even the females as קדושת
עולה, kedushat olah, does not take effect on the blemished animals. Okay,
now רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar אומר ימכרו ויקחו אותם מן. omer yamchu
v'yikchu otam min. Now the last point of the משנה, now this
is, our גרסא is רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, but that's problematic because
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says it's all בדק הבית, so the מפרשים
Mefarshim switch this to רבי אלעזר, Rebbe Elazar, a different תנא, tanna,
who says that when you sanctify not only animals do they get
קדושת עולה, kedushat olah, like what רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon just said,
רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua just said, but even when you sanctify other
things that are fit for the מזבח, they get קדושת עולה. kedushat
olah. Like what? Wine, oil, flour, birds, meaning so also yeah not
only cattle and sheep, even birds. So everything that is fit for
the מזבח in one way or another, with this generic קדושה Kedushah,
gets קדושת עולה kedushat olah and you sell it and use the
proceeds for an עולה olah and the thing itself you sell to
somebody who's going to use it for the מזבח. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי אבהו Rebbe Abahu בשם רבי שמעון
בן לקיש, bshem Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish, טעמא דרבי אלעזר, ta'ama d'Rebbe
Elazar, what's the reason of רבי אלעזר? Rebbe Elazar? He goes beyond
that earlier פסוק, pasuk, that earlier פסוק pasuk was בבקר babakar was
about sheep and cattle, not about everything. So where does he get
his stuff from? So the reason of רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar that
says רבי יהושע's Rebbe Yehoshua position applied even to other things is
דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו, daber el aharon v'el banav, the same
פסוק pasuk we quoted before, אשר יקריב להשם לעולה, asher yakriv l'hashem
l'olah, הכל קרב עולה, hakol kareiv olah, everything. Everything that's ראוי למזבח,
ra'uy l'mizbe'ach, even flour and wine etc. לרצונכם תמים זכר, l'ratzonchem tamim
zachar, so unblemished male, יכול אפילו עופות? yachol afilu ofos? תלמוד לומר
בבקר ולא עופות. talmud lomar babakar v'lo ofos. So now what does
this mean? יכול אפילו עופות? yachol afilu ofos? עופות ofos you do
bring, according to him you do get קדושת עולה kedushat olah and
you sell the proceeds. Here's what it means. And this is how
he's going to sort of get out of what the פסוק pasuk
seems to limit. He says what it doesn't say is, he doesn't
say bring, if
everything gets a קדושת עולה kedushat olah and there are birds, what
should you do with the birds? Bring them as an עולה. olah.
Why does he say sell the birds? Ah, so the way he's
reading the פסוק pasuk is when you give this generic קדושה, Kedushah,
the only thing that can be brought itself as opposed to being
sold... is sheep and cattle. Okay, anything else has to be sold
and the proceeds have to be used. So רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua
learns from this פסוק Pasuk that only sheep and cattle get קדושת
עולה. Kedushas Olah. Nothing else gets קדושת עולה. Kedushas Olah. He says
no, everything, everything that's fit למזבח, la-mizbeach, even wine and flour gets
קדושת עולה. Kedushas Olah. What is the emphasis of sheep and cattle
as the dividing line? Only sheep and cattle can be brought themselves.
Other things you have to sell and bring it for and bring
the proceeds for an עולה. Olah. And the irony is, here you
have a bird, unblemished, it doesn't matter male or female, sanctified with
קדושת עולה, Kedushas Olah, that in fact can be brought itself. But
since it originated from some generic קדושה, Kedushah you're not allowed to
bring it itself and you have to sell and use the proceeds.
Of course, can you sell it without a מום? Do you have
to wait until it gets a מום? Right, not clear. But that's
how רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar says.
בבקר Ba-bakar means only no, what's in the פסוק?
Pasuk? I don't know, look it up, look up the whole פסוק.
Pasuk. Okay, so now. רבי ירמיה רבי יוחנן רבי בון בר
חייה הוו יתבין, Rebbe Yirmiyah, Rebbe Yohanan, Rebbe Bun bar Chiyya havo
yasvin, so they were sitting, דאמרי תמן, de-amri taman, and they said
over there, תמן אמר רבי יוחנן טעמיה דרבי שמעון שכן נקבה שבעוף
כשירה לבוא עולה. Taman amar Rebbe Yohanan tameih de-Rebbe Shimon she-ken nekeivah
she-be-of kesheirah lavo olah.
Finally now we're getting to a little bit of the issue. Over
there a minute ago we had the discussion
that רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yohanan said what is the reasoning that רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon says that when you sanctify for an עולה, Olah,
when you sanctify a female for an עולה, Olah, it gets it
gets קדושה Kedushah and it makes a תמורה because an עולה Olah
as a bird can be brought as a can be a female
so it's somewhat in the פרשה. Parsha. That's what we just said.
וכמא הכא Ve-chama hacha so how can he say this here? Meaning
what's he saying here that's
problematic? ומה הכא? Ve-mah hacha? Exactly. So how come there he says
the קדושה Kedushah, what? Right. He says look what's going on. Over
there we say if you're מקדיש Makdish it, the fact that a
bird could be brought as an עולה Olah enough puts it in
the פרשה. Parsha. But here we're saying when you're מקדיש makdish it
generically, you don't bring the bird as an עולה. Olah. You're basically
keeping putting the bird in a fundamentally different פרשה. Parsha. What's going
on here? What's the difference? Okay, so let's take a look at
the answer. So אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rebbe Yosi, היי מעשה, Hai
maiseh, the first case was כהדא דאמר רבי שמואל בשם רבי זעירא.
ke-hada de-amar Rebbe Shmuel be-shem Rebbe Zeira. Like רבי שמואל Rebbe Shmuel
said in the name of רבי זעירא. Rebbe Zeira. כל שאינו יכול
לקרוב לא הוא ולא דמיה לא קדשה אלא הקדש תמיד. Kol she-eino
yachol likrov lo hu ve-lo dameha lo kadsheih ela hekdesh tamid. If
you can't sanctify it or its value, okay, it only is קדוש
קדושת דמים. Kedushas Damim. Now what does that mean? So ואת
אמר יאות Ve-at amar ya'os and you said properly let's let's spell
it out. להקריבה אינך יכול. Le-hakrivah eincha yachol.
When you gave it a generic קדושה, Kedushah you can't bring this
bird as an עולה. Olah. Obviously if you sanctified it as an
עולה Olah you can, that's a פסוק Pasuk in the תורה. Torah.
But if you gave it this generic קדושה, Kedushah you can't bring
as an עולה Olah דכתיב בבקר ולא עופות de-chtiv ba-bakar ve-lo ofot
because we just said that's how רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar reads the
פסוק Pasuk that this generic קדושה kedusha. does not let you bring
the bird unblemished. לפדותה אינך יכול. Lifdosah eincha yachol.
Now here's the question I asked. So it's unblemished, okay, it's sanctified,
what should you do with it? But you can't redeem it why
שאין לעוף פדיון. she-ein la-of pidyon. There's a הלכה halacha that a
bird you can never you can never transfer the קדושה kedusha, even
with a blemish. So basically you gave this generic קדושה, kedusha, what's
going to happen to the bird? You can't bring it itself because
of this פסוק Pasuk according to רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar that when
it's generic and applies to birds you can't bring the bird itself.
You can't redeem it. Okay, so that's when he said לא קדשה
אלא הקדש תמיד lo kadsheih ela hekdesh tamid if you can't use
it and you can't use
its proceeds. לפום כן צריך מימר לא קדשה אלא קדושת דמים. Le-pum
ken tzarich meimar lo kadsheih ela Kedushas Damim. Okay, now what does
this say to answer you know a type of a קדושה kedusha
for a בדק הבית? So what does this do to answer the
question? Oh
wait, we're not done. Okay, so wait let's keep on going. Okay,
so חברייא בשם רבי יוחנן Chavrayya be-shem Rebbe Yochanan so the sort
of the חברה, Chevreh, the colleagues in the name of רבי יוחנן.
Rebbe Yochanan. רבי אבהו בר ניהיי אמרי קומי רבי אילא בשם רבי
יוחנן. Rebbe Abahu bar Nihay amri kumi Rebbe Ila be-shem Rebbe Yochanan.
טעמא דהין תניא Ta'ama de-hen tanya but the reason of the other
תניא Tanya of the תנא Tana meaning the רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar
that says of that I'm sorry the other תנא Tana that says
wait a minute
yes that according to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon it does not get
קדושה kedusha because and he rejected hold on I'm getting lost
one second just
one more second.
Okay, so basically, no, no, now we're onto a different point. So
basically, what seems to be saying is the following, is that, I
mean, it doesn't really, it's not so clear, but it seems to
be saying that yes, it's different approaches. Meaning, according to one approach
before was that a נקבה nekeva was enough in the פרשה, parsha,
and therefore, when you're מקדיש makdish a נקבה nekeva לעולה, le'ola, because
of the birth, it's enough in the פרשה. parsha. But in this
case, in our משנה, when we're explaining רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, who
says that the birds do not get the קדושת עולה, kedushat ola,
that's based on his approach of this type of how he reads
this פסוק, pasuk, when it starts with this generic קדושה. What was
the question? The question was the following. Okay, again, this was a
case where I'm telling you, it's the מפרשים mefarshim themselves, I mean,
may have a big debate how to try to make sense out
of this. But basically,
what I'm saying, please, please accept my apologies if my explanations don't
always make 100% sense. I do not believe it's because of my
lack of full understanding, or at least lack of full understanding of
what everybody else is saying, as, you know, these סוגיות sugyot are
intrinsically problematic, okay? I'll take a degree of responsibility for it. But
anyway, but these are, it's not like there's an obvious פשט pshat
here that's being missed. Anyway, what I'm saying is the following, is
that is that
the question presumably is the following. We said we're explaining רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says when you give a generic
קדושה, right, that the birds cannot be brought themselves based on a
פסוק, pasuk, and therefore, you know, whatever, they're sold, they're sold, etc.
So they're seen as the birds are seen as fundamentally like a
different out of the פרשה. parsha. Whereas before we said that if
you sanctify a female for an עולה, ola, it's meaningful because as
a bird it would be able to be brought and fundamentally is
in the פרשה. parsha. So make up your mind, what do you
say? And the answer, which is again not clear, it seems to
be that look, when you do it in this generic way, that's
when it falls between the cracks. When you do it in this
generic way based on a פסוק, pasuk, it can't be brought itself,
and again through the proceeds because אין ein birds don't have a
פדיון, pidyon, and that's where it does get pushed out of the
פרשה parsha and that where it does get sort of fall between
the cracks. In the other case, when you were מקדיש something explicitly,
then that presumably would make it enough relevant for that discussion of
עושה תמורה. oseh tmura. Okay, so let's now move on to the
next point. חבריה בשם רבי יוחנן, Chavraya beshem Rabbi Yochanan,
so the friends in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי
אבא בר ניקרי אמר קומי רבי אילא בשם רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Abba
bar Nikri amar kumei Rabbi Ila beshem Rabbi Yochanan: טעמתא דהן תניא,
Ta'amta dehein tanya, the reason of the other תניא. tanya. Which other
תניא? tanya? So presumably what we're talking about is רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, who says nothing is gets קדושה, any a female never gets
the, if you use the wrong gender, it's always out of the
פרשה parsha and it never gets קדושה to be עושה תמורה. oseh
tmura. What's the reason for that? Because he follows on the following
פסוק: pasuk: ואם כל בהמה טמאה אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן להשם.
Ve'im kol behema tme'ah asher lo yakrivu mimenah korban l'Hashem. מה תלמוד
לומר טמאה? Mah talmud lomar tme'ah? So this is a saying you
sanctified a animal, you try to sanctify it as a קרבן, korban,
but it was a טמאה. tme'ah. Now presumably that means it was
like, let's say I don't know, a camel, you tried to sanctify
as a קרבן. korban. So it says that, it says you don't
use as a קרבן, korban, you sell it, you use the proceeds,
etc. Okay? So that's the case. So that would be a case
of אינו עושה תמורה. eino oseh tmura. You tried to sanctify a
camel. So here's the question is going to be the following. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that nothing is עושה תמורה, oseh tmura, right?
It's if you try to do a female and so on, it's
completely out of the פרשה. parsha. So the question is the idea
that an animal that you try to sanctify as a קרבן korban
is out of the פרשה parsha is this פסוק pasuk that says
you tried to sanctify an animal that's actually טמאה, tme'ah, like a
camel, okay? So the question is what would fall into that category
similar to sanctifying the camel? That's a way of thinking about it.
Okay, so let's take a look. מה תלמוד לומר טמאה? Mah talmud
lomar tme'ah? What does it mean טמאה? tme'ah? אלא אפילו טמאה באותו
השם. Ela afilu tme'ah be'oto hashem. So טמאה tme'ah would be even
something that would be inappropriate. Meaning, טמאה tme'ah is not just a
camel. Anything, that's what he's saying. He understands this פסוק pasuk the
same way before we read the פסוק pasuk לעולה, le'ola, everything becomes
an עולה. ola. He's reading this פסוק pasuk that anything that's inappropriate
is טמאה. tme'ah. So the reason of the תנא tanna that says
that it does not עושה תמורה oseh tmura when you try to
sanctify a female for an עולה, ola, and that the wrong gender
does not, anything that's inappropriate is in the category of טמאה. tme'ah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, now the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge
it. לקשיא, Lekashya, it's difficult. דכתיב והעמיד והעריך, Dechtiv vehe'emid vehe'erich, so
it says here that you sort of stand it up and you
assess the value and you transfer the value. ורבי זעירא בשם רבי
אלעזר לא אמר כן, VeRabbi Zeira beshem Rabbi Elazar lo amar ken,
אלא, ela, and that means that you put it completely out of
the פרשה. parsha. But we don't teach that. Why what does he
teach? ואם כל בהמה טמאה אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן להשם. Ve'im
kol behema tme'ah asher lo yakrivu mimenah korban l'Hashem. כל שאינו ראוי
ליקרב לא כאן ולא במקום אחר. Kol she'eino ra'uy likarev lo kan
velo bemakom acher. Okay, only if it's really like טמאה. tme'ah. It
can't be brought here and it can never be used in any
other context as a קרבן. korban. אינו עושה תמורה. Eino oseh tmura.
יצאת נקבה לעולה, Yatzat nekeva le'ola, but a נקבה nekeva for
an עולה ola wouldn't be in the טמאה tme'ah category. אף על
פי שאינו ראוי ליקרב כאן ראוי ליקרב במקום אחר. Af al pi
she'eino ra'uy likarev kan ra'uy likarev bemakom acher. Even though it can't
be used for this, it can be used for... or something else?
So therefore, no, טמאה tmeia only means fully טמאה, tmeia, something that's
completely inappropriate. Something like a female is enough generally in the פרשה,
parsha, okay, and therefore it would not have this הלכה halacha of
אינה עושה תמורה. eina osa tmura. It would actually be able to
make a תמורה. רבי אבון רבי בון בעו קמי רבי זעירא. Rabbi
Avun, Rabbi Bun boei kamei Rabbi Zeira. So now they ask one
minute, הרי הרובע והנרבע. harei haroveiah vehanirva. How about an animal that's
been used in an act of bestiality? The הלכה halacha is that
שאינם ראויים ליקרב לא כאן ולא במקום אחר, she'einam reuyim likarev lo
kan velo bemakom acher, you can't use it for any type of
a קרבן, korban, but you know what's the הלכה is? If you
sanctify them as a קרבן, korban, they have enough קדושת מזבח that
they're עושי תמורה. osei tmura. והרי אין עושי תמורה. veharei ein osei
tmura. So why isn't that in the category of טמאה? tmeia? That's
something that's completely inappropriate. אמר לון אף אני לא אמרתי אלא טמאה
ממש. amar lon af ani lo amarti ela tmeia mamash. Okay, you
know what? You're right. Forget it. It just means really טמאה. tmeia.
Okay. Now, if you say that then, so that's in a way
then proving רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We tried to say טמאה tmeia
meant inappropriate, but in the way, and I'm sorry, it's the שטתיה
shititei of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We tried to say like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that טמאה tmeia meant anything that would be somehow
inappropriate,
maybe distinguishing between females and other things, but anyway, not literally טמאה,
tmeia, using it to mean inappropriate. But in the end we say,
no, it means טמאה ממש. tmeia mamash. So therefore everything else really
should be עושה תמורה. osa tmura. So now we have וקשיא בדא
דתניא מאי בערכין. vekashei beda detanya mai bearichin. And therefore it says
that this is something that you redeem and it's not עושה תמורה.
osa tmura. So in the end, we're trying to say what is
the idea that if it's out of the פרשה parsha it's עושה
תמורה, osa tmura, if it's not עושה תמורה osa tmura it's because
that would fall in the טמאה tmeia category. Okay, and we would
say טמאה tmeia means anything inappropriate. But then the גמרא rejected. You
can't say it means anything inappropriate, there's something that are completely inappropriate
and they're still עושי תמורה. osei tmura. So you cannot try to
say that anything you don't like goes into the טמאה tmeia category.
So we're back with the question about, you know, about sanctifying a
female, would it have enough קדושה to be עושה תמורה osa tmura
or not? Let's finish the
פרק. perek. Enough קדושת מזבח. Alright. Finally, the rest is so easy.
Okay. אחת לשלשים יום משערין את הלשכה. achas lishloshim yom meshari et
halishka. Once every thirty days they would fix the prices for the
money that they were buying from the things they were buying for
the שקל, shekel, like the wine and the oil and so on.
כל המקבל עליו לספק סלתות. kol hamikabel alav lesapek solatos. Now we'll
see what it means. You are going to provide the flour for
the מזבח. Like I said, it's major volume, but you got to
deal with the following conditions. Okay, once a month we set the
prices. So Charlie, here, you're my supplier and we say fine. Okay,
based on what it looks like it's going to be now, based
on what the prices are now, whatever, you're going to pay me
בארבע be'arba per שקל shekel of barley, of for flour. And we'll
we can renegotiate the price next ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but that's
what we're saying now for this month. Once a month we set
the price. So they said בארבע, be'arba, you're going to give me
four סאה. se'ah. עמדו משלוש, amdu mishalosh, and now in the middle
of the month it's now it's gone up in price and really
it's three for a שקל. shekel. יספיק מארבע, yaspik me'arba, you still
got to give me based on the deal. Okay, that was the
deal, but look at the other way. משלוש, mishalosh, if at the
beginning of the month we agreed on three, ועמדו מארבע, ve'amdu me'arba,
and the price went down and now it's going four for a
שקל, shekel, יספיק מארבע, yaspik me'arba, you give me four. I always
get the benefit. שיד הקדש על העליונה. sheyad hekdesh al ha'elyona. הקדש
hekdesh always gets the benefit. אם התליעה, im hitli'ah, now
סולת התליעה לו. soles hitli'ah lo. Let's say the flour got wormy,
okay, even after you delivered it, even after I paid for it,
I can always return it. You know, I always have the right
of return. It's like, you know, so what our return policy is,
we force our our our suppliers to have the return policy that
you are always entitled to return for a full refund until
you use it, presumably.
ואם החמיץ
יין החמיץ לו. ve'im hichmitz yayin hichmitz lo. If it turns sour,
the supplier's has to take that responsibility. אינו מקבל מעותיו, eino mekabel
ma'osav, you do not get to hold on to your money. It
doesn't necessarily mean we don't give you your money, but you don't
get to hold on to your money עד שיהא מזבח מרצה, ad
sheyehei mizbeiah mirtze, until it actually gets offered up on the altar.
After that, it's a point of no return. No, I assume פיגול
pigul is different. Okay, it's not something that happens to the thing
itself. Okay, so תני בשם רבי שמעון, tani beshem Rabbi Shimon, now
we're told in the name of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and we
quoted this earlier, מיד היו מקבלין את מעותיהן. miyad hayu mekabelin es
ma'oseihen. No, we wouldn't do that to poor Charlie. Actually, what we
would give him his money right away. Why aren't we then afraid
that it'll get wormy or it'll get spoiled? הכהנים זריזים הם, hakohanim
zerizim heim, they'll use it right away. So therefore we don't make,
we're not so unfair that we make him either wait to literally
get his money or wait to be entitled to his money. Once
we actually get the product, we accept that we cannot return it.
הדרן עלך פרק תמורה. hadaran alach perek tmura. Yes, and we wouldn't
use it.
Okay, that was really fun.